Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Memorabilia 5149 MB
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Memorabilia
1883-1969
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen (BRT)
5149 MB
4.5 cubic feet
4.5 linear ft.
Memorabilia.
Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Memorabilia including plaques, badges, buttons, pendants, dues receipts, constitution booklets, paperweights, railroad link, pin and spike, and many other miscellaneous items
5932039
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, May 14, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 07, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen was founded in 1883 in Oneonta, N.Y. as a protective and insurance organization. By the time of its merger with three other railroad labor unions to form the United Transportation Union in 1969, it had the greatest membership of any of the operating railroad brotherhoods.
The Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen (BRT) was established to represent members' interests in obtaining a satisfactory contract with management. The first Canadian lodge was established in Moncton, New Brunswick in 1885, and the first Ladies' Auxiliary was organized in Fort Gratiot, Mich. in 1889. These records reflect the union's political and fraternal activities as well as its actions in the areas of collective bargaining, grievances, and railroad and labor legislation. As the largest of the unions which merged to form the United Transportation Union in 1969, the bulk of its then current files formed the basis for the files now held in the merged union's headquarters.
The rail service members of the BRT included conductors and their assistants, dining car stewards, ticket collectors, train baggagemen, brakemen, and train flagmen. The yard service members of the BRT included yardmasters, yard conductors, switchtenders, foremen, flagmen, brakemen, switchmen, car tenders, operators, hump riders, and car operators. In 1933, the BRT organized interstate bus operators, and included them under BRT contracts held with U.S. bus companies.
BRT officers were elected at the Grand Lodge Convention of the Brotherhood, held every 4 years. The principal officers included a president, an assistant to the president, a general secretary-treasurer, Canadian and national legislative representatives, a senior vice-president, BRT representative, and National Railroad Board of Adjustment representative. The BRT had four governing boards: the Board of Directors, Board of Trustees and Insurance, Board of Appeals, and Executive Board.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5021: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Additional Records 5102: Emergency Board No. 129, Long Island Railroad and the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, Locals 517 and 1090, Records 5149: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Records 5149 P: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Photographs 5348: W.P. Kennedy as President of the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen against the Long Island Railroad Company Court Documents 5446: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Ledger 5612: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Moosic Tunnel Lodge no.93 Meeting Minutes 5623: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Legislative Board of New York Files 5631: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Chicago, Milwaukee, St. Paul and Pacific Railroad General Committee File 5647: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Joppa Lodge (Toledo, OH) Minute Books 5894: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Additional Railroad Booklets 6268 P: Joint Committee of Adjustment for the Rock Island System's Order of Railway Conductors and Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Photograph 6312 P: Judith Sullivan Kowalczyk Collection of Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Photographs 6312 PUBS: Judith Sullivan Kowalczyk Collection of Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Publications 6312m: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Annual Report of the Legislative Board 6405 PUBS: William Sharp Collection of The Railroad Trainmen's Journal 6480 MB: Paul Berger Collection of Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Memorabilia
Implements, utensils, etc.; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen --Collectibles
5932039
- BRT - buttons, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Buttons - "Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen"; "Dickerson Rund Lodge 632, 1921"; "Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, BRT"; "In Unity There Is Strength. In Strength There Is Victory. In Victory There Is Peace And In Peace There Is Security"A.F. Whitney,
- BRT - badges (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Badges - All three are two sided, one side red, one black. All three are "Bradley Lodge No. 719, L.A. to B.R.T., St. Cloud, Minn.". "Warden" has gold crossed axes hanging from top. "Legislative Representative" has a law scroll hanging on it. "Treasurer" h
- BRT - badges (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Badges - All three are two sided, one side red, one black. All three are "Bradley Lodge No. 719, L.A. to B.R.T., St. Cloud, Minn.". "President"; "Past President w/3 crossed gavels; "Vice President" w/2 crossed gavels; "Secretary" w/2 crossed leaves.
- BRT - badges (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Badges - All three are two sided, one side red, one black. All three are "Bradley Lodge No. 719, L.A. to B.R.T., St. Cloud, Minn.". "Pianist" w/scroll & pen; "Conductress" w/crossed batons; "Chaplin" w/Bible; "Outer Guard" & "Inner Guard" w/crossed swo
- BRT - badges (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Badges - Two are double sided, one is red/green/white and other side is "In Memoriam" side and is black. These are for "Member", "R.E. Knowlton Lodge No. 357, B. of R.T., Fond Du Lac, Wis."; "Denver, Colorado, 1916", has a pendant in shape of train stat
- BRT - badges, 1935-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Badges - "75th Diamond Jubilee, B.R.T., Oneonta, N.Y. Sept. 23, 1958" w/pendant depicting a railway station; "Cleveland, Ohio, Souvenir, Second Quadrennial Convention, Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen.May 1939"; "Seventh Annual State Convention, Brothe
- BRT - badges, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Badges - Three are double sided, green/white/red on one side, second side is black "In Memoriam". "Foot Board Lodge No. 804, B. of R.T., St. Paul, Minn."; "Col. B.F. Haines Lodge, No. 406, B. of R.T., Port Morris, N.J."; "Northern Central Lodge, No. 413
- BRT - buttons & pendant (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Buttons - BRT service pins for 10, 15, 20, 25, 30, 40, 45 & 50 years. Differ in shapes. Other buttons - ""Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen"; "Past President Trainmen"; pendant - "Brotherhood", with the head of an armor on top with working mouth piece,
- BRT - buttons, push-pins, patches (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Push-pins - "B of RT"; "Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen"; "-- Years Membership B of RT" for 25, 30, 35, 40, 50, 55, 60 [owned by James L. Karney, Switchman-Eng., 4-Man AT & SF Ry., La Junta, Colorado; Buttons - "Member, BLF & E, Organized 1873"; "Memb
- BRT - push-pins (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Push-pins - membership pins of various shapes/styles for the years of service - 10, 15, 20, 25, 30, 35, 40; "Brotherhood.Bus Division"; "C.R.R. of N.J., Veteran"; "Jersey Central Lines, Safety Award, 10 years"
- BRT - badges (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Badges - All three are two sided, one for "In Memoriam". Two are for "Ottawa River Lodge No. 185, B.R.T. Ottawa, Ont."; third one is for "F.H. Phillips Lodge No. 37, B. of R.R.T., West Albany, N.Y.
- BRT - comics [The Double-crossing Als!, The Alibi Als] (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Two comics - both about wages
- BRT - badges & push-pin, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Three badges are two sided, one side of each is black "In Memoriam". Two badges are red/green/white on one side w/lettering - "City Point Lodge, No. 507" one is "Inner Guard", one is "Outer Guard", both "B.R.T. Boston, Mass." Badge for "L.A., B. of R.R.T.
- BRT - pocket protectors, pen and pencil clip (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Pocket protectors, blue w/white flap and lettering "Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, It Doesn't CostIt Pays to Belong to the Brotherhood"; pen - "BrotherhoodCleveland, Ohio"; pencil clip - "Brotherhood of Railroad"
- BRT - wood and metal 'stamps' of symbols for BRT (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Stamps of the symbols used by BRT, made out of metal and attached to small wooden blocks
- BRT - Delegate credential, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  "Grand Lodge, Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, Delegate's Credential" - Lodge No. 961 [employers certificate allowing an employee to go to the convention as a Delegate]
- BRT - Honor Roll book (Box 2, Folder 6)
  "Honor Roll, Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen" - book full of names of union members that died in World War II.
- BRT - Souvenir Strike Ballot, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Discussion of issues vs. blank ballot, for or against strike in response to wage reduction authorized by Decision No. 147 of the US Railroad Labor Board, August 29, 1921.
- BRT - Official Receipt for dues (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Actual receipts for dues paid by members of the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen.
- BRT - Miscellaneous papers, 1911-1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Dues paid receipt, convention name tags for "New York State Association Brotherhood of Sept. 22-23-24, 1958, Albany, NY"; copy of "Preamble of Our Constitution"; invitation to a union meeting; union Propoganda; invitation to "First Annual Ball, Bitte
- BRT - Comic books (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Comic books - "Cliff Merritt And the Very Candid Candidate" & "Cliff Merritt Sets the Record Straight"
- BRT- Constitution booklet, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  "Constitution and General Rules of the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen"
- BRT - Decals (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Decals - "Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Bus Division"
- BRT- Rosters, 1922-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  "Roster of -- Convention, Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen" for the following (27th, 32nd, 31st, 22nd, 30th, 23rd, 29th, 26th,28th, 33rd, 25th)
- BRT - Paperweight, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Membership card incased in plastic - "Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, Traveling Card"
- BRT - Gold railroad link, pin and spike (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Railroad spike, pin and link painted gold.
- BRT - Gold painted (wooden) railroad link and pin (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Wooden replica - Railroad pin and link painted gold.
- Charles Pratt Photos (Box 4, Folder 1)
  3 Railroad photos with Charles Pratt
- Charles Pratt papers, 1890-1969 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  2 Prayer cards from Charles Pratt's funeral; 2 copies of Charles Pratt's birth certificate; Comic books - "Cliff Merritt And the Very Candid Candidate" & "Cliff Merritt Sets the Record Straight;" Acknowledgement letter of Charles Pratts resignation from t
- Buttons/lapel pins from BRT (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Service pins for the years of 20, 25, 30, 35, 40, 45, 50, 55; Membership buttons/lapel pins from the BRT
- Memory Book - Charles Pratt funeral, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Book of signatures from Charles Pratt's funeral
- Large aluminum plaque -- Brotherhood * Railroad * Trainmen (Box 5)
  - Large aluminum plaque: Brotherhood * Railroad * Trainmen (Box 5, Folder 1)
    snapshot available
- Images digitized from the collection. (Box 6)
- Images digitized from the collection. (Box 7)